Guide to the Leo Rudolph Etzkorn papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Leo Rudolph Etzkorn papers,
1881-1976
[Bulk dates: 1937-1976]
Etzkorn, Leo Rudolph, 1897-1979?
1.05 linear feet ( 2.5 document boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#0403
4078743
This collection is comprised of the personal and professional papers of Leo R. Etzkorn, the treasurer of the New York Library School Association.
Biographical Note and History of the New York State Library School Association
Leo R. Etzkorn (1897-1979) was the treasurer of the New York State Library School Association from 1949 until his death. Etzkorn graduated from Whitman College in 1921, and went on to study Library Science at the New York State Library School, from which he graduated in 1924. His wife, Helen Hinman Martin, also attended the school and graduated with the class of 1926. Etzkorn was the chief librarian of the Fall River Public Library in Fall River, Massachusetts from 1929 until 1931; in 1931, he left Massachusetts to become a librarian at the public library in Paterson, New Jersey. He was president of the New Jersey Library Association from 1937 until 1938.
Etzkorn's alma mater, The New York State Library School, was founded at Columbia College by Melvil Dewey as The School of Library Economy in 1887. The school was renamed in 1889, when it was transferred to the State University at Albany. In 1926 the school was transferred back to Columbia, merging with the New York Public Library School to become the Columbia School of Library Service.
The New York State Library School Association, Inc. represented the alumni of that school. The Association was officially dissolved in 1966, and its assets turned over to Columbia University School of Library Service, though it continued "unincorporated" and informally for some time after.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of the papers of Leo R. Etzkorn, who was the treasurer of the New York State Library School Association from 1949 until 1979. Much of the collection is composed of treasurer's reports, account books, membership lists, and minutes from annual meetings and meetings of the Board of Directors of the Association, including some that date from before Etzkorn's tenure as treasurer. General correspondence includes letters addressed both to Etzkorn and to other members of the Board of Directors, and many include updates on various members. Legal correspondence relates to proxy voting and the incorporation and dissolution of the association; a separate folder contains documents related to the transfer of funds to Columbia University at the time of the Association's dissolution. Included with papers relating to Joseph L. Wheeler is a copy of his book, The Mount Independence-Hubbardton 1776 Military Road, and genealogical research on the Moulton, Hinman, Barber, Swallow, and Wheeler families.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged alphabetically.
Subjects
New York State Library School; New York State Library School Association; Columbia University; Columbia University.--School of Library Service; Barber family; Conrad, Mildred King; Etzkorn, Leo Rudolph; Kaiser, John Boynton, 1887-1973; Rhodes, Isabella Knox, 1885-; Wheeler, Joseph Lewis, 1884-1970; Van Rees, Cornelius, 1899-1973; Genealogy; Libraries; Library education--New York (State)--Societies, etc.; Account books.; Correspondence; Financial records; Minutes
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Acquisition
Christine E. Little via the School of Library Service Gift 1980 M80 of Library Service
Selected Related Material-- at Columbia
John Boynton Kaiser Papers, 1928-1971, MS#0689, Rare Book & Manuscript Library.
New York State Library School Records 1887-1967, MS#0928, Rare Book & Manuscript Library.
Finding aid in repository; folder level control.
- Series I
  - Account Books, 1894-1964 (4 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 1 to 4)
  - Annual Meetings--Invitations and Minutes, 1938-1966 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bank Accounts, 1963-1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Board of Directors--Officer Lists and Meeting Minutes, 1937-1974 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Columbia University, 1966-1976 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Conrad, Mildred King--Bequest, 1962-1968 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - New York State Library School Association Constitution, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence--General, 1939-1974 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence--Legal, 1954-1963 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - New York State Library School--Visits, 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    (Pamphlets)
  - van Norman, Louina--Debt, 1924-1948 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Members--Geographical Lists and Necrologies, 1951-1966 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Members--Geographical List, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    (Index Cards)
  - Personal Financials, 1956-1964 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Register of Members, 1887-1926 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Treasurer's Reports, 1956-1966 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Wheeler, Joseph L., 1881-1969 (Box 3, Folder 2)